In this video, I'd like to tell you about learning curves.
本节课我们介绍学习曲线
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
Learning curves is often a very useful thing to plot.
绘制学习曲线非常有用
If either you wanted to sanity check
也许你想检查你的学习算法
that your algorithm is working correctly,
运行是否一切正常
or if you want to improve the performance of the algorithm.
或者你希望改进算法的表现或效果
And learning curves is a
那么学习曲线
tool that I actually use
就是一种很好的工具
very often to try to
我经常使用学习曲线
diagnose if a physical learning algorithm may be
来判断某一个学习算法
suffering from bias, sort of variance problem or a bit of both.
是否处于偏差 方差问题 或是二者皆有
Here's what a learning curve is.
下面我们就来介绍学习曲线
To plot a learning curve, what
为了绘制一条学习曲线
I usually do is plot
我通常先绘制出Jtrain
j train which is, say,
也就是训练集数据的
average squared error on my training
平均误差平方和
set or Jcv which is
或者Jcv 也即交叉验证集数据的
the average squared error on my cross validation set.
平均误差平方和
And I'm going to plot
我要将其绘制成一个
that as a function
关于参数m的函数
of m, that is as a function
也就是一个关于训练集
of the number of training examples I have.
样本总数的函数
And so m is usually a constant like maybe I just have, you know, a 100
所以m一般都是一个常数 比如m等于100
training examples but what I'm
表示100组训练样本
going to do is artificially with
但我要自己取一些m的值
use my training set exercise. So, I
也就是说我要自行对m的取值
deliberately limit myself to using only,
做一点限制
say, 10 or 20 or
比如说我取10 20或者
30 or 40 training examples and
30 40组训练集
plot what the training error is and
然后绘出训练集误差
what the cross validation is for this
以及交叉验证集误差
smallest training set exercises. So
好的 那么我们来看看
let's see what these plots may look
这条曲线绘制出来是什么样子
like. Suppose I have only
假设我只有一组训练样本
one training example like that
也即m=1
shown in this this first example
正如第一幅图中所示
here and let's say I'm fitting a quadratic function. Well, I
并且假设使用二次函数来拟合模型
have only one training example. I'm
那么由于我只有一个训练样本
going to be able to fit it perfectly
拟合的结果很明显会很好
right? You know, just fit the quadratic function. I'm
是吧 用二次函数来拟合
going to have 0
对这一个训练样本拟合
error on the one training example. If I
其误差一定为0
have two training examples. Well the quadratic function can also fit that very well. So,
如果有两组训练样本 二次函数也能很好地拟合
even if I am using regularization,
即使是使用正则化
I can probably fit this quite well.
拟合的结果也会很好
And if I am using no neural regularization,
而如果不使用正则化的话
I'm going to fit this perfectly and
那么拟合效果绝对棒极了
if I have three training examples
如果我用三组训练样本的话
again. Yeah, I can fit a quadratic
好吧 看起来依然能很好地
function perfectly so if
用二次函数拟合
m equals 1 or m equals 2 or m equals 3,
也就是说 当m等于1 m=2 或m=3时
my training error
对训练集数据进行预测
on my training set is
得到的训练集误差
going to be 0 assuming I'm
都将等于0
not using regularization or it may
这里假设我不使用正则化
slightly large in 0 if
当然如果使用正则化
I'm using regularization and
那么误差就稍大于0
by the way if I have
顺便提醒一下
a large training set and I'm artificially
如果我的训练集样本很大
restricting the size of my
而我要人为地限制训练集
training set in order to J train.
样本的容量
Here if I set
比如说这里
M equals 3, say, and I
我将m值设为3
train on only three examples,
然后我仅用这三组样本进行训练
then, for this figure I
然后对应到这个图中
am going to measure my training error
我只看对这三组训练样本
only on the three examples that
进行预测得到的训练误差
actually fit my data too
也是和我模型拟合的三组样本
and so even I have to say
所以即使我有100组训练样本
a 100 training examples but if I want to plot what my
而我还是想绘制
training error is the m equals 3. What I'm going to do
当m等于3时的训练误差
is to measure the
那么我要关注的仍然是
training error on the
对这三组训练样本进行预测的误差
three examples that I've actually fit to my hypothesis 2.
同样 这三组样本也是我们用来拟合模型的三组样本
And not all the other examples that I have
所有其他的样本
deliberately omitted from the training
我都在训练过程中选择性忽略了
process. So just to summarize what we've
好的 总结一下
seen is that if the training set
我们现在已经看到
size is small then the
当训练样本容量m很小的时候
training error is going to be small as well.
训练误差也会很小
Because you know, we have a
因为很显然
small training set is
如果我们训练集很小
going to be very easy to
那么很容易就能把
fit your training set
训练集拟合到很好
very well may be even
甚至拟合得天衣无缝
perfectly now say
现在我们来看
we have m equals 4 for example. Well then
当m等于4的时候
a quadratic function can be
好吧 二次函数似乎也能
a longer fit this data set
对数据拟合得很好
perfectly and if I
那我们再看
have m equals 5 then you
当m等于5的情况
know, maybe quadratic function will fit to stay there so
这时候再用二次函数来拟合
so, then as my training set gets larger.
好像效果有下降但还是差强人意
It becomes harder and harder to
而当我的训练集越来越大的时候
ensure that I can
你不难发现 要保证使用二次函数
find the quadratic function that process through
的拟合效果依然很好
all my examples perfectly. So
就显得越来越困难了
in fact as the training set size
因此 事实上随着训练集容量的增大
grows what you find
我们不难发现
is that my average training error
我们的平均训练误差
actually increases and so if you plot
是逐渐增大的
this figure what you find
因此如果你画出这条曲线
is that the training set
你就会发现
error that is the average
训练集误差 也就是
error on your hypothesis grows
对假设进行预测的误差平均值
as m grows and just to repeat when the intuition is that when
随着m的增大而增大
m is small when you have very
再重复一遍对这一问题的理解
few training examples. It's pretty
当训练样本很少的时候
easy to fit every single
对每一个训练样本
one of your training examples perfectly and
都能很容易地拟合到很好
so your error is going
所以训练误差将会很小
to be small whereas
而反过来
when m is larger then gets
当m的值逐渐增大
harder all the training
那么想对每一个训练样本都拟合到很好
examples perfectly and so
就显得愈发的困难了
your training set error becomes
因此训练集误差就会越来越大
more larger now, how about the cross validation error.
那么交叉验证集误差的情况如何呢
Well, the cross validation is
好的 交叉验证集误差
my error on this cross
是对完全陌生的交叉验证集数据
validation set that I haven't seen and
进行预测得到的误差
so, you know, when I have
那么我们知道
a very small training set, I'm
当训练集很小的时候
not going to generalize well, just
泛化程度不会很好
not going to do well on that.
意思是不能很好地适应新样本
So, right, this hypothesis here doesn't
因此这个假设
look like a good one, and
就不是一个理想的假设
it's only when I get
只有当我使用
a larger training set that,
一个更大的训练集时
you know, I'm starting to get
我才有可能
hypotheses that maybe fit
得到一个能够更好拟合数据的
the data somewhat better.
可能的假设
So your cross validation error and
因此 你的验证集误差和
your test set error will tend
测试集误差
to decrease as your training
都会随着训练集样本容量m的增加
set size increases because the
而减小 因为你使用的数据越多
more data you have, the better
你越能获得更好地泛化表现
you do at generalizing to new examples.
或者说对新样本的适应能力更强
So, just the more data you have, the better the hypothesis you fit.
因此 数据越多 越能拟合出合适的假设
So if you plot j train,
所以 如果你把Jtrain和Jcv绘制出来
and Jcv this is the sort of thing that you get.
就应该得到这样的曲线
Now let's look at what
现在我们来看看
the learning curves may look like
当处于高偏差或者高方差的情况时
if we have either high
这些学习曲线
bias or high variance problems.
又会变成什么样子
Suppose your hypothesis has high
假如你的假设处于高偏差问题
bias and to explain this
为了更清楚地解释这个问题
I'm going to use a, set an
我要用一个简单的例子来说明
example, of fitting a straight
也就是用一条直线
line to data that, you
来拟合数据的例子
know, can't really be fit well by a straight line.
很显然一条直线不能很好地拟合数据
So we end up with a hypotheses that maybe looks like that.
所以最后得到的假设很有可能是这样的
Now let's think what would
现在我们来想一想
happen if we were to increase
如果我们增大训练集样本容量
the training set size. So if
会发生什么情况呢
instead of five examples like
所以现在不像画出的这样
what I've drawn there, imagine that
只有这五组样本了
we have a lot more training examples.
我们有了更多的训练样本
Well what happens, if you fit a straight line to this.
那么如果你用一条直线来拟合
What you find is that, you
不难发现
end up with you know, pretty much the same straight line.
还是会得到类似的一条直线假设
I mean a straight line that
我的意思是
just cannot fit this
刚才的情况用一条直线不能很好地拟合
data and getting a ton more data, well
而现在把样本容量扩大了
the straight line isn't going to change that much.
这条直线也基本不会变化太大
This is the best possible straight-line
因为这条直线是对这组数据
fit to this data, but the
最可能也是最接近的拟合
straight line just can't fit this
但一条直线再怎么接近
data set that well. So,
也不可能对这组数据进行很好的拟合
if you plot across validation error,
所以 如果你绘出交叉验证集误差
this is what it will look like.
应该是这样子的
Option on the left, if you have already a miniscule training set size like you know,
最左端表示训练集样本容量很小 比如说只有一组样本
maybe just one training example and is not going to do well.
那么表现当然很不好
But by the time you have
而随着你增大训练集样本数
reached a certain number of training
当达到某一个容量值的时候
examples, you have almost
你就会找到那条最有可能
fit the best possible straight
拟合数据的那条直线
line, and even if
并且此时即便
you end up with a much
你继续增大训练集的
larger training set size, a
样本容量
much larger value of m,
即使你不断增大m的值
you know, you're basically getting the same straight line,
你基本上还是会得到的一条差不多的直线
and so, the cross-validation error
因此 交叉验证集误差
- let me label that -
我把它标在这里
or test set error or
或者测试集误差
plateau out, or flatten out
将会很快变为水平而不再变化
pretty soon, once you reached
只要训练集样本容量值达到
beyond a certain the number
或超过了那个特定的数值
of training examples, unless you
交叉验证集误差和测试集误差就趋于不变
pretty much fit the best possible straight line.
这样你会得到最能拟合数据的那条直线
And how about training error?
那么训练误差又如何呢
Well, the training error will again be small.
同样 训练误差一开始也是很小的
And what you find
而在高偏差的情形中
in the high bias case is
你会发现训练集误差
that the training error will end
会逐渐增大
up close to the cross
一直趋于接近
validation error, because you
交叉验证集误差
have so few parameters and so
这是因为你的参数很少
much data, at least when m is large.
但当m很大的时候 数据太多
The performance on the training
此时训练集和交叉验证集的
set and the cross validation set will be very similar.
预测效果将会非常接近
And so, this is what your
这就是当你的学习算法处于
learning curves will look like,
高偏差情形时
if you have an algorithm that has high bias.
学习曲线的大致走向
And finally, the problem with
最后补充一点
high bias is reflected in
高偏差的情形
the fact that both the
反映出的问题是
cross validation error and the
交叉验证集和训练集
training error are high,
误差都很大
and so you end up with
也就是说 你最终会得到一个
a relatively high value of
值比较大Jcv
both Jcv and the j train.
和Jtrain
This also implies something very
这也得出一个很有意思的结论
interesting, which is that,
那就是
if a learning algorithm has high
如果一个学习算法
bias, as we
有很大的偏差
get more and more training examples,
那么当我们选用更多的训练样本时
that is, as we move to
也就是在这幅图中
the right of this figure, we'll
随着我们增大横坐标
notice that the cross
我们发现交叉验证集误差的值
validation error isn't going
不会表现出明显的下降
down much, it's basically fattened
实际上是变为水平了
up, and so if
所以如果学习算法
learning algorithms are really suffering from high bias.
正处于高偏差的情形
Getting more training data by
那么选用更多的训练集数据
itself will actually not help
对于改善算法表现无益
that much,and as our figure
正如我们右边的
example in the figure
这两幅图所体现的
on the right, here we had only five training.
这里我们只有五组训练样本
examples, and we fill certain straight line.
然后我们找到这条直线来拟合
And when we had a ton
然后我们增加了更多的训练样本
more training data, we still
但我们仍然得到几乎一样的
end up with roughly the same straight line.
一条直线
And so if the learning algorithm
因此如果学习算法
has high bias give me a lot more training data.
处于高偏差时
That doesn't actually help you
给我再多的训练数据也于事无补
get a much lower cross validation
交叉验证集误差或测试集误差
error or test set error.
也不会降低多少
So knowing if your learning
所以 能够看清你的算法正处于
algorithm is suffering from high
高偏差的情形
bias seems like a useful
是一件很有意义的事情
thing to know because this can
因为这样可以让你避免
prevent you from wasting a
把时间浪费在
lot of time collecting more training
收集更多的训练集数据上
data where it might just not end up being helpful.
因为再多的数据也是无意义的
Next let us look at the
接下来我们再来看看
setting of a learning algorithm
当学习算法正处于高方差的时候
that may have high variance.
学习曲线应该是什么样子的
Let us just look at the
首先我们来看
training error in a around if
训练集误差
you have very smart training
如果你的训练集样本容量很小
set like five training examples shown on
比如像图中所示情形
the figure on the right and
只有五组训练样本
if we're fitting say a
如果我们用很高阶次的
very high order polynomial,
多项式来拟合
and I've written a hundredth degree polynomial which
比如这里我用了100次的多项式函数
really no one uses, but just an illustration.
当然不会有人这么用的 这里只是演示
And if we're using a
并且假设我们使用
fairly small value of lambda,
一个很小的lambda值
maybe not zero, but a fairly
可能不等于0
small value of lambda, then
但足够小的lambda
we'll end up, you know,
那么很显然 我们会对这组数据
fitting this data very well that with
拟合得非常非常好
a function that overfits this.
因此这个假设函数对数据过拟合
So, if the training
所以 如果训练集
set size is small, our training
样本容量很小时
error, that is, j train
训练集误差Jtrain
of theta will be small.
将会很小
And as this training set size increases
随着训练集样本容量的增加
a bit, you know, we may
可能这个假设函数仍然会
still be overfitting this
对数据或多或少
data a little bit but
有一点过拟合
it also becomes slightly harder to
但很明显此时要对数据很好地拟合
fit this data set perfectly,
显得更加困难和吃力了
and so, as the training set size
所以 随着训练集样本容量的增大
increases, we'll find that
我们会发现Jtrain的值
j train increases, because
会随之增大
it is just a little harder to fit
因为当训练样本越多的时候
the training set perfectly when we have
我们就越难跟训练集数据拟合得很好
more examples, but the training set error will still be pretty low.
但总的来说训练集误差还是很小
Now, how about the cross validation error?
交叉验证集误差又如何呢
Well, in high variance
好的 在高方差的情形中
setting, a hypothesis is
假设函数对数据过拟合
overfitting and so the
因此交叉验证集误差
cross validation error will remain
将会一直都很大
high, even as we
即便我们选择一个
get you know, a moderate number
比较合适恰当的
of training examples and, so
训练集样本数
maybe, the cross validation
因此交叉验证集误差
error may look like that.
画出来差不多是这样的
And the indicative diagnostic that we
所以算法处于高方差情形
have a high variance problem,
最明显的一个特点是
is the fact that there's
在训练集误差
this large gap between
和交叉验证集误差之间
the training error and the cross validation error.
有一段很大的差距
And looking at this figure.
而这个曲线图也反映出
If we think about adding more
如果我们要考虑增大训练集的样本数
training data, that is, taking
也就是在这幅图中
this figure and extrapolating to
向右延伸曲线
the right, we can kind
我们大致可以看出
of tell that, you know the
这两条学习曲线
two curves, the blue curve
蓝色和红色的两条曲线
and the magenta curve, are converging to each other.
正在相互靠近
And so, if we were to
因此 如果我们将曲线
extrapolate this figure to
向右延伸出去
the right, then it
那么似乎
seems it likely that the
训练集误差很可能会
training error will keep on
逐渐增大
going up and the
而交叉验证集误差
cross-validation error would keep on going down.
则会持续下降
And the thing we really care about is the cross-validation error
当然我们最关心的还是交叉验证集误差
or the test set error, right?
或者测试集误差 对吧
So in this sort
所以从这幅图中
of figure, we can tell that
我们基本可以预测
if we keep on adding training
如果继续增大训练样本的数量
examples and extrapolate to the
将曲线向右延伸
right, well our cross validation
交叉验证集误差将会
error will keep on coming down.
逐渐下降
And, so, in the high
所以 在高方差的情形中
variance setting, getting more
使用更多的训练集数据
training data is, indeed,
对改进算法的表现
likely to help.
事实上是有效果的
And so again, this seems like a
这同样也体现出
useful thing to know if your
知道你的算法正处于
learning algorithm is suffering
高方差的情形
from a high variance problem, because
也是非常有意义的
that tells you, for example that it
因为它能告诉你
may be be worth your while
是否有必要花时间
to see if you can go and get some more training data.
来增加更多的训练集数据
Now, on the previous slide
好的 在前一页和这一页幻灯片中
and this slide, I've drawn fairly
我画出的学习曲线
clean fairly idealized curves.
都是相当理想化的曲线
If you plot these curves for
针对一个实际的学习算法
an actual learning algorithm, sometimes
如果你画出学习曲线的话
you will actually see, you know, pretty
你会看到基本类似的结果
much curves, like what I've drawn here.
就像我在这里画的一样
Although, sometimes you see curves
虽然如此
that are a little bit noisier and
有时候你也会看到
a little bit messier than this.
带有一点噪声或干扰的曲线
But plotting learning curves like
但总的来说
these can often tell
像这样画出学习曲线
you, can often help you
确实能帮助你
figure out if your learning algorithm is
看清你的学习算法
suffering from bias, or variance or even a little bit of both.
是否处于高偏差 高方差 或二者皆有的情形
So when I'm
所以当我打算
trying to improve the performance of
改进一个学习算法
a learning algorithm, one thing
的表现时
that I'll almost always do
我通常会进行的一项工作
is plot these learning
就是画出这些学习曲线
curves, and usually this will
一般来讲 这项工作会让你
give you a better sense of whether there is a bias or variance problem.
更轻松地看出偏差或方差的问题
And in the next video
在下一节视频中
we'll see how this can
我们将介绍如何判断
help suggest specific actions is
是否应采取具体的某个行为
to take, or to not take,
来改进学习算法的表现
in order to try to improve the performance of your learning algorithm.